They would not have done the two year
$100 million deal with $60 million
guaranteed if they thought guy we're
basically punting on 2026. Now, and and
there were other teams that stood ready
to make a push for Daniel Jones if he
didn't get tagged. You know, that tells
you that the level of play was high
enough that it makes sense the Colts are
doubling down and believing in Daniel
Jones. But the good news is you still
got Jonathan Taylor, you got a strong
running game, you resigned Alec Pierce.
You you have the ability to in other
words take some of the load off the
quarterback because um you know, he's
got better weapons than he's had at
times in his
Hey Colts fans, I'm JJ Stankevitz and
welcome in to another episode of the
Colts Show, an Indianapolis Colts
podcast. We are presented by our friends
at Microsoft Surface Co-pilot Plus PC.
As we teased it, Tom Pelissero is on the
pod today. You know him from NFL
Network, one of my favorite insiders in
the game. Great dude. We talked a little
bit about the golf simulator they had at
the owners meetings to start out off the
podcast which with by the way, like you
want to talk about like a punter's
chance? Just like give me a golf club
and six shots and somehow I parked a
couple of shots on the simulator they
had down in Arizona within like four
feet of the hole. Which like would be
one of the best shots I've ever had in
my entire life if it was on an actual
golf course. So, that is not indicative
of my ability to play golf. What is
indicative is Tom Pelissero's ability to
talk about the Colts about some really
interesting stuff regarding how money is
spent and how you we should think about
contracts like the one Alec Pierce got,
like the one Daniel Jones got. We might
see these big stickers, you know, on
these prices of oh my god, that's so
much money. But comparatively it's
actually not not There's a way to think
about it that we get into. I won't spoil
anything else on that. Um if you haven't
caught up with our previous podcast from
the owners meetings, last week I had NFL
Network's Ian Rapoport and The
Athletic's Dane Brugler on the pod. The
week prior to that, I had Colts owner
and CEO Carlie Irsay Gordon on the pod.
A great conversation with Carlie right
there. And then get this, next week
players are back in the building here on
56th Street. But by the time next week's
podcast comes out, the Colts will be
back in the building for voluntary
off-season workouts and the start of the
voluntary off-season program. We're
going to have a lot of stuff coming over
the next couple of months with OTAs
getting underway, with these kind of
voluntary meetings, workouts, and stuff
with players back here. Stay tuned with
us here on the Colts Show. Remember to
rate, review, and subscribe wherever you
get your podcast. Subscribe to us on
YouTube as well at Colts. All right,
without further ado, let's get to my
conversation with NFL Network's Tom
Pelissero.
It is my pleasure to be joined here on
the Colts Show by Tom Pelissero from NFL
Network. Tom, thanks for the time today.
Appreciate it.
>> Glad to be here. Glad we're no longer
near that golf simulator where you
kicked my ass earlier. That was good.
>> I mean, like I told you, we have this
like par three course behind the Colts
facility that I just go out there and I
I ping shots from 105, 116, what it what
which it it was today.
>> Four feet, one inch from the pin. Yeah,
but it didn't win. It didn't I I got it
within 38. This is complete This is
great. I got it within 38 on Sunday, the
first day of the owners meetings that I
was here and I was leading it most of
the day until Ed Policy, president of
the Green Bay Packers, parked it at one,
too. But then someone else got it four
inches from the pin.
Yeah, I was like 14 feet. I was pretty
proud of that, but you had just gone, so
then I felt terrible.
>> Yeah, it was kind of a tough scene. I
mean, I got I After we're done with
this, I'm going to go check what Shane
Steichen got.
>> He told me he beat me. I don't think he
beat you.
>> well, that's good cuz I usually lose the
closest to the pin competition to him.
Anyways, we're here to talk about the
Colts, the 2026 Colts.
Um
what do you think, Tom, success looks
like for this team in 2026? Like very
broadly.
>> Uh well, I think that the first thing is
like any team, you want to be better
than you were the year before. And
that's a pretty high bar when you think
of when the Colts were healthy prior to
the injuries hitting, prior to Saquon
getting hurt, Daniel Jones dealing with
his injuries,
they were in the line for the number one
seed. The baseline has to be the
playoffs. I don't think that I'm
breaking news on that. Uh for Carlie to
see the types of progress that she wants
to see, certainly for Chris and Shane,
they believe they've got a really good
team in terms of a personnel perspective
here. You have to be able to take that
next leap forward. Now, this is not the
AFC South of several years ago. You have
the Jaguars who just were a really good
team, had a heck of a season in Liam
Coen's first season. Obviously, the
Texans three for three in getting there
um under DeMeco Ryans, winning playoff
games um under DeMeco Ryans, they're
certainly not going to be a pushover in
the division. We'll see how Tennessee
progresses. Once again, a reset there.
They got a young quarterback in Cam
Ward. So, it's not as if you're going to
you know, waltz into the playoffs being
an eight and nine division winner or
something. You're talking about having
to go out, win 10 plus games to be in
that mix. There's no reason based on
what we saw last year that they can't
get there. Um but it comes down to how
quickly is Daniel Jones 100% not just
health-wise with the Achilles, but from
a production perspective, how quickly is
he playing like Daniel Jones? Um you
know, health across the roster is going
to be a significant part of it as well.
And then are some of these moves that
we've seen, even the you know, the ones
that are a little bit more under the
radar, are they going to help fill some
of those gaps that we saw with the Colts
last season?
>> Yeah. You know, Arden Key, Cam
Taylor-Britt, you know, those type of
guys adding some depth on defense. Um
with Daniel,
what's your understanding of kind of
like the the progression in the rehab
process to get back? You know, you
mentioned him being at 100%, but like is
it realistic for him to be at 100% week
one, start training camp, week eight?
Like where where does that sort of hit
in your understanding?
>> and that's the complicated part is you
don't know. It's It's one thing to say a
guy's 100% healthy and cleared for a
return to action, but in terms of when
he needs to break the pocket, when he
needs to move around, how confident is
he? Confident is he in terms of throwing
the football and his footwork? You know,
we've seen it with older players like
Aaron Rodgers and Kirk Cousins. Again,
those guys being significant number of
years older, you would think Daniel
Jones who's dealt with injuries in the
past, he knows what rehab is about. Um
you'd think that he would potentially be
a faster healer. But it really took
those guys a whole year after the
injury, a whole season to get back and
okay, they're starting to look like um
they can play like themselves again. And
so, that's an unknown. It's something
they'll be evaluating. I'm sure they're
going to have a really good plan in
terms of what his workload looks like. I
wouldn't think that he's doing a great
deal um in the spring, probably
individual type stuff. Training camp,
ramping him up, making sure you're not
overloading him. He's got to be the one
who's knows. You know, he knows his body
better than anybody. In September, you
know, is he going to be fully ready to
be back? You're talking about right
around nine months if we're talking
about the start of the season here. Um
so, we'll see. Um but they would put it
this way, they would not have transition
tagged him. They would not have done the
two year $100 million deal with $60
million guaranteed if they thought guy
we're basically punting on 2026. Now,
and and there were other teams that
stood ready to make a push for Daniel
Jones if he didn't get tagged. You know,
that tells you that the level of play
was high enough that it makes sense the
Colts are doubling down and believing in
Daniel Jones. It's really just a matter
of how quickly is he able to knock the
proverbial rust off or really feel like
himself again. But the good news is you
still got Jonathan Taylor, you got a
strong running game, you resigned Alec
Pierce. You you have the ability to in
other words take some of the load off
the quarterback because um you know,
he's got better weapons than he's had at
times in his career. You do such a good
job kind of disseminating these this
information on contracts. You just kind
of talked a little bit about it with
Daniel. Something that I always think
about with contracts is yeah, you see
these average annual values that are
huge and you see these guarantees that
are huge. But in the case of Alec
Pierce, I looked this up. His average
annual value as a percentage of the cap
is 9.5%.
This is per Over the Cap. Historically,
that puts him in the range with Mike
Williams who's a to me a really good
comp for Alec Pierce. Chris Godwin,
another high-end, you know, kind of
number two type of guy. Tyler Lockett,
Vincent Jackson, and Jameson Williams is
at 9.6%. Mhm. Is that a Like how should
you think how should we think about the
like woah, Alec's getting that much
money versus like well, this is really
the historical comparison. Like how do
you balance that?
>> Well, let's start with the fact that 13
years ago, the salary cap is hovering
around the $123 million mark. It's now
over $300 million.
>> Alec Pierce got almost that entire mark
in his contract.
>> Correct. That's how much um the thing
has grown. I mean, or think of it this
way, back in 2018 and everyone's minds
were blown by Kirk Cousins getting a
basically fully guaranteed, functionally
guaranteed deal. That was three years,
$84 million. We saw a center get almost
the identical contract from the Raiders
this year with the same um type of a
structure. That just shows you how much
it's grown. Um the receiver market has
exploded because you had, you know,
Justin Jefferson resetting the bar
obviously last year, it's Ja'Marr Chase
um resetting the bar more recently,
Jaxon Smith-Njigba as well. For Alec,
you know, there was a position scarcity.
He was the one guy out there. And if he
had become an unrestricted free agent
and signed elsewhere, it would have been
by far the biggest unrestricted free
agent receiver contract in NFL history.
Not because he's the greatest receiver
in the NFL or the greatest who's ever
hit the market. He's a really, really
good player who does something rare,
which is make big plays. If you go back
at guys who have had as many catches as
Alec has had or have 1,000 yards and
also have an average of what he averaged
last year per catch, you're in rarefied
air. It's basically DeSean Jackson did
it twice and Mike Wallace did.
>> Mike Wallace, yeah. So, those are like
two of the And Mike Wallace went and got
a huge deal with the Dolphins which was
like $12 million a year and that blew
everyone's minds. Um you know, obviously
DeSean Jackson was a you know, if not a
Hall of Famer, he's a really, really
good player for a long time.
>> with Alec is those guys were smaller.
They were a little more slight of frame.
Alec is 6'4", 215.
>> unicorn and that's and that's why. I
mean, there were going to be I don't
know how many of them would have gone
upwards of $30 million per year, but
there were going to be a bunch of teams
making huge pushes. I mean, there was,
you know, if not quite a blank check
situation, pretty close that he was
going to have out there if he had gotten
to the market. Listen, he he wanted to
be in Indianapolis. He and Daniel wanted
to be together. It got a little edgy
there, you know, down at the end when
they ultimately they can't strike a deal
with Daniel in advance of the tag. So,
they got to make the decision we're
going to transition tag him. If Alec
wanted to get to the market and wanted
to get out there, he could have done
that. In the end, he's where he wants to
be. He's had a ton of productivity with
the Colts. Last year was his best season
and you would think it's only going to
get better. He's [clears throat] still a
young guy. He's a core locker room guy.
And it's a great point in terms of, you
know, the percentage of cap because if
you compare things, you know, to where
they were again, even 12, 13 years ago.
I mean, Aaron Rodgers was the highest
paid quarterback in the NFL circuit 2013
at 22 million a year. And he was the
highest paid for several years at that
number. We now have quarterbacks making
nearly triple that.
Um it's just, you know, the context of
it I think is important here. They
didn't They Put it this way. They did
not overspend relative to the market.
Your value is what someone is willing to
pay you. And there were other
[clears throat] teams ready and willing
to pay Alec Pierce this much if not
more. Now, we talk a lot about Daniel
Jones and Alec Pierce. Obviously, those
are kind of the two big off season moves
that the Colts made. Is there like an
X-factor who's somebody who's maybe off
the national radar, but you look at this
team and and this could be a coach, a
staff member, a player, someone who
you're like, that guy could be a reason
or that person could be a reason why the
Colts could find success in 2026? I
mean, I think that there's a lot of them
like on any team. I do think that, you
know, bringing like a guy like Cam
Taylor Britt. And that's a relationship
thing where he played for Lou Anarumo,
played a lot of games. He started. He
played well. If you We were talking
about a year ago, Cam Taylor Britt hits
the market, he might be one of those
guys who's getting, um you know, the
big-time contracts that we see in free
agency. This year was a one-year, wasn't
quite minimum, but it was a one-year
low-risk flyer on a guy who has all the
upside in the world. It just went
sideways for whatever reason last year
in Cincinnati. Now, he's back with the
very coach under which he played his
best football. If you think about it,
that's been a big part of you know, the
Colts journey here. They traded for
Sauce because they didn't have a corner.
And Chidobe Awuzie Ward's future remains
up in the air at this point because of
the concussions and he's got to decide
his future. The Colts have to decide his
future. You know, if you're going to
play in the NFL, you need multiple
corners. If a guy like Cam Taylor Britt
can come in and, you know, be either
your two or your three,
you can do worse than that from a
physical perspective. So, you know,
moves like that and again, we're there's
still parts and waves of this of this
off season, too. You have the draft.
That's going to be big. They don't have
a first-round picks. You're going to be
having to try to figure out value and
who's going to slot in and help you
right now. But it's also, you know,
additional trades. It's also potentially
the guys that you pick up after the
draft, you know, some of those veterans
that are sitting out there. I mean,
Chris Ballard has never been afraid to,
you know, I know that fans sometimes get
frustrated, oh, he's not making the big
free agent moves. Well, he's taking some
pretty big swings in trades. You know,
one bringing in DeForest Buckner, one
bringing in Sauce Gardner. I know those
are like several years apart. Um but
when it's a, you know, a targeted type
of a need, he's not been afraid to go
there. I wouldn't be surprised at all if
you continue to see moves here over
these next couple of months. And buying
them in Chidobe Awuzie Ward last year
were pretty big swings in free agency.
Um I want to get you out of here on
this, Tom.
The Carlie Irsay Gordon's been around
these owners meetings, you know, for a a
long time. She's been She's had a, you
know, a heavy presence within the Colts
franchise, within the the building for
for a while. But this is now her first
full year as principal owner and CEO.
Like when you talk to other people about
Carlie, her name comes up. Her
leadership or ownership comes up.
What are those conversation What have
kind of been the tenor of those
conversations around the league with
some of your colleagues just about the
the new era of Colts ownership? Well, I
think that, you know, I haven't spoken
to a ton of people about it, but what I
would say is
um
she's put in the time. And I think that
that's the biggest thing that everybody
wants. I mean, you know, the track
record It's just like when she's making
a decision at the end of the year of do
you make major moves at head coach and
GM or do you stick with Shane and Chris?
Uh she stuck with him, but because
there's no track record, nobody quite
knew uh how she was going to operate. In
a year where you had a lot of teams, a
lot of those ones that seemed 50/50 on
their head coaches or GMs, and almost
all of them fell to firings where we had
so many head coach vacancies. Um the
fact that she stuck with them, I mean,
it did reflect I think the patience that
Jim uh had throughout his career. Um you
know, I don't know Obviously, there's a
lot of respect for Jim within the
league. Um you know, but Carlie's her
her own person. And so, we'll see, you
know, as things move forward here. Yeah,
last year was so unique. I mean, there's
not a lot of examples of a team starting
out seven and one, eight and two and
then completely folding like that.
>> Quarterback breaks his leg, tears his
Achilles.
>> And you have to ask yourself, what was
the real part? Was it the start of the
season or the second half of the season?
Carlie's willing to give uh Shane and
Chris an opportunity to to show that
they were right. And, you know, the fact
that she's not, you know, living
somewhere else and she just pops in on
game days and then makes a decision. I
do think that there's a level of respect
that comes with that. It's not an
over-involvement. It's not as if, you
know, she's moving all the chess pieces
across the board. But what she is doing
is educating herself as she did for
years and all the time that she spent on
the sideline, all the time she spent
with Joey Elliott, all the time that she
spent like familiarizing herself with
personnel and all the other aspects of
it. Like, if I'm a fan, that's what I
want. I don't necessarily want the
person who it's like, well, they're
going to follow their whims and it's
going to be a dictatorship and they're
going to do whatever they want. No, it's
like, make decisions for the right
reasons, educate yourself, familiarize
yourself, understand people, but also
understand the business. I mean, I know
Chris said it publicly that he went to
her and said, "Hey, if you got to fire
me, I totally understand." That's Chris.
You know, that's that's That's Chris.
Yeah. That's him, but it's also, you
know, she she made her own decision on
this and she'll be monitoring this
season closely. I think everybody has
high expectations, rightly so, because
they really are doubling down on what
they had last season. It's not going to
be the exact same team, but there's
going to be a lot of pieces that there
that are the same. If they can capture
it, if they can find a way to scrape
together wins early in the season when
maybe Daniel's not quite 100%, we'll
see. Um that'll set themselves up to be
able to make a run at this thing. And I
think it's going to exciting season for
football fans in Indianapolis. Great
insight. Really appreciate it. Tom
Pelissero from NFL Network. Thanks for
joining me today. Yeah.